<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Publick affections, pressed in a sermon before the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament: Upon the solemn day of humiliation, Febr. 25. 1645. / By Anthony Burgesse, pastour of Sutton-Cold-field: now minister at Laurence Jewry London, and a member of the Assembly of Divines. Published by order of that House.</title>
            <author>Burgess, Anthony, d. 1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77846</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5653</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E325_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200622</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861322</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861322</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113455</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77846)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113455)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E325[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Publick affections, pressed in a sermon before the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament: Upon the solemn day of humiliation, Febr. 25. 1645. / By Anthony Burgesse, pastour of Sutton-Cold-field: now minister at Laurence Jewry London, and a member of the Assembly of Divines. Published by order of that House.</title>
                  <author>Burgess, Anthony, d. 1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.Y. for Thomas Vnderhill, at the Bible in Woodstreet.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLVI. [1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Order to print on verso of first leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Numbers XI, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermonsx --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:113455:1"/>
            <head>Die Mercurii, Febr. 25. 1645.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, that S.</hi> Robert Harlow, <hi>and Col.</hi> Purfrey <hi>do give thanks to M.</hi> Burgeſſe, <hi>and M.</hi> Goodwin, <hi>for the great pains they took in the Sermons they preached this day, at the intreaty of the Houſe of Commons, at S.</hi> Margarets <hi>Weſtminſter (it being the day of publick Humiliation) and to deſire them to print their Sermons. It is alſo ordered, That none ſhall preſume to print their Sermons without licence under their hand-writing.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Elſ. <hi>Cler. Parl. D. Com.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>I appoint <hi>Thomas Underhill</hi> to print my Sermon, and no man elſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ANTHONY BURGESSE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113455:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Publick Affections, PRESSED IN A SERMON Before the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT: Upon the Solemn day of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, <hi>Febr.</hi> 25. 1645.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> ANTHONY BURGESSE, Paſtour of Sutton-Cold-field: Now Miniſter at <hi>Laurence Jewry</hi> London, and a Member of the Aſſembly of DIVINES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Order of that Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J. Y.</hi> for <hi>Thomas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderhill,</hi> at the Bible in Woodſtreet. M.DC.XLVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113455:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113455:2"/>
            <head>TO The Honourable Houſe OF COMMONS, Aſſembled in Parliament at WESTMINSTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy SENATORS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Viciſsitude of Gods Providence to men in great place, ſomtimes pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down thoſe who are lifted up on high, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain raiſing up thoſe who were laid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,
<pb facs="tcp:113455:3"/>may justly provoke all Magistrates to walk with fear and trembling; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, there is a greater then they are. All earthly Potentates and Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are, before God, but as ſo much pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſt, which, when hee breatheth on, is ſoon ſcattered away. Hence, <hi>Pſalm 2.</hi> the great Ones of the earth are exhorted to <hi>kiſſe the Sonne, leſt hee be angry;</hi> and a little of his anger is too heavie for the ſhoulders of any mortall men. Be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected therefore with your own nothing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, comparatively to Gods greatneſſe, and advance his Truth, Worſhip, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Many States have ſtumbled upon Christ, as a Stone of offence; and hee again hath fallen upon them, grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them to powder. The Lord make you ſo bleſſed, that you may not be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at any thing which is Chriſts; and
<pb facs="tcp:113455:3"/>fill you ſo with faith, that you may be fully perſwaded in your hearts, that the ſurest posture of defence for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is, when it is put into a ſubmiſsion unto the Scepter of Christ Jeſus. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God hath done much for you, yet great is the need you ſtill have of his Goodneſſe, Wiſdome, and power to you. The ſhippe coming into the harbour may miſcarry, as well as that in the wide O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean: And, certainly, the buſineſſes of your Warre and Peace, of the Church and State, of Diviſions and Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, are of ſo great concernment, that hee ſeeth nothing at all, who doth not judge you in as great a neceſsity of Gods good Providence, as at the very first. Therefore, after all the great ſucceſſe which God hath vouchſafed unto you, be not high-minded, but fear: keep a ſure
<pb facs="tcp:113455:4"/>interest in God, and provoke him not by any ſinnes; but ſo manage all things belonging to God and men, with piety and justice, that God from heaven may proſper you, and men on earth praiſe you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble ſervant in CHRIST, ANTHONY BURGESSE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113455:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED Before the Honourable Houſe OF COMMONS, At the publick Faſt, <hi>Febr.</hi> 25. 1645.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>NUMB. 11.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Have I conceived all this people? Have I begotten them, that thou ſhouldeſt ſay unto mee, Carry them in thy boſome (as a nurſing father beareth the ſucking-childe) unto the land which thou ſwareſt unto their fathers?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Deliverance of the Iſraelites out of Egypt, that iron furnace, and the conducting of them through the wilderneſſe unto the land of Canaan, is ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and remarkable an hiſtory, that many after-deliverances given unto the Church of God, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed alluſively to this: Thus the bringing out of Babylon tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, The reſcuing of the Church out of Babylon ſpirituall, is ſet down with words relating to this grand mercy; yea, it is made
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113455:5"/>typicall of that great redemption, purchaſed by Chriſts bloud: For this is a peculiar thing to Gods word, that not onely words, but things themſelves do ſignifie; onely we muſt not make a type or allegory, but where the holy Ghoſt giveth ground, leſt wee ſhould have <hi>tot ſacramenta, quot ingenii acumina,</hi> (as was ſaid of <hi>Origen) as many myſterious notions, as men have fancies.</hi> This Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory therefore will ſerve for our Meridian; and there is ſcarce any Kingdome or Church, but they have had their Egypts, their <hi>Pharaoh's,</hi> their bricks to make: and God in great mercy doth ſometimes raiſe up ſome <hi>Moſes</hi>'s and <hi>Aarons</hi> for them, providing a land of Canaan, as the comfortable iſſue of their former la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. The ſlaviſh and miſerable condition of the Iſraelites is related <hi>Exod.</hi> 2. as alſo Gods pitie to them, in moſt emphaticall words, <hi>ver.</hi> 24, 25. hee <hi>heard their groaning, remembred his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, looked upon them, and had reſpect unto their cauſe:</hi> This heap of words doth expreſſe, after the manner of men, the great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and bowels of God to help, though this was delayed to very extremity, according to that known ſaying, <hi>Quando du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicantur lateres, venit</hi> Moſes.</p>
            <p>Now, after the people of Iſrael had been freed from this bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, inſtructed in the will of God, covenanted obedience with him, ſeen his wonderfull power, injoyed his mighty preſence, ſo that they could not be more ſafe then they were under his protection, not more free then they were under his lawes, not more rich then they were under his proviſion; yet in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter begins a narration of their manifold mutinies againſt God, and their faithfull governours: ſo true is that, <hi>Subditis ſemper gravis est praeſens ſtatus;</hi> and, <hi>Vulgus eſt ſemper querulum:</hi> not knowing how to bear either their miſeries, or their remedies. The firſt mutiny ſeemeth to be for their long march, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. whereupon a fire from the Lord conſumed them. It is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that in all their former rebellions before the Law was given, (except that of the Calfe) God never puniſhed them; but ſince the Law given, hee puniſhed them ſeverely: This was (ſay ſome) to ſhew the nature of the Law, that it worketh wrath; or becauſe their ſins committed after the Law given, were againſt greater knowledge and ingagement.</p>
            <p>The ſecond mutiny begins <hi>ver.</hi> 4. (for I cannot be of their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113455:5"/>minde, that make the former and this all one) and this was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned firſt by the mixed multitude that was with them, <hi>viz.</hi> the Egyptians, and other nations; and the plague upon them did quickly infect the Iſraelites: They murmure becauſe they have nothing but Manna; and becauſe this was a ſacrament, and a type of Chriſt and his graces, their ſin was ſpirituall as well as corporall: whereupon <hi>Moſes,</hi> to ſhew their ingratitude, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth occaſion to deſcribe this Manna, what it was. The peoples rage and ingratitude putteth <hi>Moſes</hi> into a ſinfull paſſionate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, though there was alſo good zeal in it. The popiſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters make this zeal of <hi>Moſes</hi> pure fire: but that cannot be; and, <hi>inſtruunt Patriarchae etiam errantes,</hi> the errours of the godly may teach, as well as their piety. That <hi>Moſes</hi> his heat was not wholly naturall, but ſomething feavouriſh, appeareth, 1. From the complaint of that truſt and charge God had committed to him; when-as, indeed, it was God his love and honouring of him. 2. In complaining of thoſe qualities that ought to be in him as a Governour, <hi>Have I conceived all this people</hi> (to be a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to them)? <hi>Have I begotten them</hi> (to be a father to them)? And this care over the people is reſembled to the fathers bearing a ſucking-child in his arms: and when <hi>Moſes</hi> complaineth, that God did ſay unto him, <hi>Bear theſe as a father,</hi> we doe not reade any-where that God commanded him in ſuch expreſſe words; but calling him to that office, was, in effect, to ſay ſo. 3. His impatience is ſeen, in deſiring to die, rather then to goe thorow that work, it being not lawfull to deſire death out of impatience for any pretence whatſoever.</p>
            <p>The Rabbins they have another reaſon why hee was in a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; becauſe, ſay they, hee ſpeaks to God in the feminine gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; for <hi>v.</hi> 15. there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: but a Friars notion upon the New Teſtament, and a Rabbins upon the Old, are much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; for the word is uſed in a feminine form, though of a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſculine gender, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.14.</p>
            <p>The Obſervations I ſhall purſue out of the Text are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God layeth a command and charge upon all thoſe whom hee raiſeth up to relieve an oppreſſed people, to doe it with tender affections to the publick: They muſt regard the Common-wealth, as the father doth the ſucking-childe in his armes.</hi> Hence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28.9. to <hi>feed a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113455:6"/>people,</hi> is, to <hi>rule them;</hi> and the word doth not ſignifie <hi>a meer ſingle feeding,</hi> but, <hi>with love and great affection:</hi> and this phraſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is frequent among Heathens: Hence <hi>Philo</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that God took Governours from following the ſheep, being uſed to a paſtorall cure, that ſo they might with greater bowels and affections govern men. And, as God, in the Old Teſtament, called ſhepherds, rather then of any other profeſſion; ſo, in the New Teſtament, he called fiſhermen, rather then others, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick imployment; and all becauſe ſuch are uſed to more pains, labour, and diligence.</p>
            <p>Obſ. 2. <hi>The ingratitude and diſcontents of people are ſuch under Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, that they make their condition very hard and uncomfortable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſ. 3. <hi>It is very hard for Governours themſelves to lead a people out of bondage into freedome, and not to provoke God much by their owne ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſ. 4. <hi>That though God doe raiſe up men on purpoſe to doe ſome great work for him, yet there will be many difficulties and ſtops in the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſ. 5. <hi>It's not enough to bring out of Egypt, but we muſt be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the matter I have choſen to treat of, is practicall, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, The Manna did not fall within the camp, or tents; ſo neither doth ſweet practicall matter in controverſies.</p>
            <p>For the firſt Obſervation, I ſhall declare in how many wayes theſe tender affections to the publick are to be ſeen:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In a deep ſenſe and feeling of publick miſeries.</hi> In this, <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah's</hi> practice is imitable; who, though hee had all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and accommodation, for himſelf, that his heart could wiſh in the Kings Court, yet was exceeding ſad, and took no notice of all his advantages, becauſe Jeruſalem was in deſolations. Chriſt, in the midſt of all his applauſe and acclamation, wept, becauſe of the evill to come upon Jeruſalem. Write after this copy, and ſay, All our own ſafety and good ſucceſſe doth not take off our hearts from the ſad thoughts about publick deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Sometimes take off your thoughts from other matters, and conſider in private how great the ſtreights, miſeries, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties of thouſands are in the three Kingdomes; eſpecially on ſuch daies as theſe are, take the advantage of your hearts. Shall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113455:6"/>ſo many families and eſtates be broken, and not your hearts? ſo many bodies lie wounded in the field, and ſhall not your hearts be wounded?</p>
            <p>Let us be ſo many <hi>Jeremiah's,</hi> making our lamentations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. And if the Prophet findes his bowels making noiſe like an harp within, even for the deſolation of a Moab, how much rather for Jeruſalem? Mee thinks, theſe dayes are rather ſpent in expecting what new thing, or witty thing wil be preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then preparing hearts to mourn, and guſh out becauſe of the breaches God hath made.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In taking heed of provoking God by our perſonall ſins.</hi> If wee love the publick, how carefull ſhall we be to ſin, leſt God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it upon the Common-wealth? When <hi>David</hi> had ſinned, and the Kingdome was viſited, how doth hee cry out, <hi>I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but what have theſe ſheep done?</hi> Injuſtice and impiety in men of office and dignity, is cruelty to the Common-wealth: The ſinnes of ſuch are like the eclipſes of the Sun, and other celeſtiall bodies, that do much corrupt the ſublunary. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, The perpetuall duration of things cometh from the ſimple and daily motion of the Sun from the Eaſt into the Weſt: but the corruption of things is, becauſe of the oblique motion of the Sun and Starres thorow the Zodiack. Reſolve then, becauſe we love the publick, there ſhall no iniquity be found in our hands, no ungodlineſſe in our families: I will not be a <hi>Jonah</hi> in the ſhip, to cauſe the tempeſts and ſtorms to ariſe. As great mens children have ſometimes other boyes whipt for their faults; ſo doth God chaſtiſe Governours upon the people, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the peoples ſins upon Governours. Conſider therefore, Is the wrath of God upon the land? what ſin may you find out of yours, or your families, that ſo, the vapours being diſperſed, there may be no more thunder?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>In abhorring all ſelf advantages to the prejudice of the publick.</hi> This is to be like a tender father: and how fully did <hi>Moſes</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe this? When God offered him great preferment, to make a great nation of him and his, he doth utterly refuſe ſuch an offer. Who hath ſincerity and faithfulneſs enough to deny ſuch a thing in our dayes, if God ſhould tender it? <hi>Tully</hi> had two wiſhes, though hee ſaw neither effected: one was, to ſee the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113455:7"/>Common-wealth free before he died: and the other, That every man might have ſuch a fortune (as he calls it) as he ſtood af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the publick. The divell doth many times proffer the glory of the world to a man, if hee will deny the publick. Be able to ſay of all ſelf-advantages, as <hi>Pliny</hi> in another caſe, <hi>Capio aliquam voluptatem, quôd hâc voluptate non capior. Hoc eſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatus, ſua negligere, &amp; eorum quos regit, curam habere.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſaith <hi>Oleaster,</hi> God made <hi>Pharaoh</hi> have a dream about the ſcarcity and famine that was to come (though ignorant of God) rather then any other, becauſe it belonged to thoſe that were in authority to provide for others: ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.21, 24. They were high expreſſions of <hi>Paul</hi> concerning his countrey-men, He could be even an Anathema for them: I will not diſpute about thoſe expreſſions, but gather this, That the heart of a man rightly ſet for the publick good of others, is more boundleſſe then the ſea, having no <hi>huc uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Faithfull diligence, and indefatigable labour to procure the good of it.</hi> Take an example from <hi>Moſes:</hi> How doth he conſume himſelf in care and labour for them, till <hi>Jethro</hi> adviſeth him to take ſome aſſiſtants? And although he had theſe, yet the burden lay moſt upon him, as appeareth by his expoſtulation: Therefore God appoints a new help of the Sanhedrim in this Chapter. It was a ſpeech of an heathen, that <hi>the burdens of men in place, are worſe then thoſe of aſſes;</hi> for they are taken off their backs while they eat or reſt, but it is not ſo with thoſe Governours that faithfully attend to the publick. The Lacedemonians in their publick Courts would have no pictures or images, that there might not be the leaſt object to draw away their minds from the matters in hand. As therefore it is ſaid of God, he is <hi>totus ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> and <hi>totus uber:</hi> an <hi>eye,</hi> becauſe of his vigilancy; and a <hi>dug,</hi> or <hi>breſt,</hi> becauſe of his ſweet nouriſhing all: the ſame is to be true of all in place.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>To eye Gods command and charge; for this God layeth upon every one in office and place, to be like a father in it.</hi> Hence were thoſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellations, <hi>Patres patriae.</hi> Now the <hi>eying</hi> of God in this duty, will make us to exceed the famous Romans, as much as the Sun doth the glow-worm. Who know not the brave exploits and great ſervices they did for the Common-wealth? The acts
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113455:7"/>of <hi>Curtius</hi> and others are almoſt incredible: but they looked not to God in theſe things; ſo that their actions were good bullion (as it were) but not a true ſtamp upon them, and therefore would not paſſe with God. It is well maintained by our Divines, yea, ſome of the School-men, <hi>Ariminenſis,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, That theſe were not works <hi>moraliter bona;</hi> becauſe, though the proxime end might be good, yet they knew not the ultimate end, which was Gods glory. Conſider therefore what obligations God puts upon you, and let your publick actions be <hi>à Deo, per Deum, ad Deum:</hi> that in ſerving the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, you may ſerve God alſo.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>To doe all things from an inward principle of affection.</hi> For, a man is not a father by reading all the Oeconomicks in the world, but it muſt be implanted in his heart: ſo neither will you be good Common-wealths-men by reading <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> or <hi>Machiavel;</hi> but by earneſt prayer to God to give you father-like affections. None but a father or mother will take pains about his childe. As hee therefore ſaid of his image that would not ſtand, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>There wants ſomething within;</hi> ſo, when thou findeſt thy heart liſtleſſe, careleſſe, ſelfiſh in publick matters, cry out, Here wants ſomething within, bowels within. What <hi>Maximus Tyrius</hi> ſaid of a ſuperſtitious man, <hi>He was Gods flatterer, not his friend:</hi> the ſame is true of many to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. Who knoweth not <hi>Nero</hi>'s <hi>Quinquenuium?</hi> His <hi>Utinam neſcirem literas?</hi> But a fatherly affection is ſolid, and reall; hee loveth it for its ſelfe. Many follow the Common-wealth, as flies doe a man that doth carry an honey-box; not for the mans ſake, but the honey. It was a brave challenge which <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> made, and the people acquitted him in it, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.3, 4, 5. yea, <hi>Paul (Act.</hi> 20.33.) goeth higher; for he ſaith, he had not deſired any of their goods.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>To mind all things that doe heale and unite.</hi> And this is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary at this time, when, by opinions and diſcontents, wee are ſcattered into ſo many pieces, that, unleſſe <hi>Democritus</hi> his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould prove true, <hi>that all things are compoſed of Atomes,</hi> there is little hope for us: and I doe not ſo much tremble at the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full effects they are likely to produce, as the cauſe from whence they come, <hi>viz.</hi> from Gods anger and diſpleaſure. <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.23.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113455:8"/>when God purpoſed to deſtroy <hi>Abimelech,</hi> he ſent an evill ſpirit between him and the men of Shechem. I have read a ſtory of two in a ſhip that were in deadly enmity one with the other, and immediately tempeſts ariſe, the ſhip is ready to be drowned, but the two men mind not to ſave that; onely one gets to one end of the ſhip, and another to the other, and would needs know which would ſink firſt; accounting it happineſs enough, though the ſhip were not ſafe, yet if one might ſurvive to ſee the other drowned: I need not apply it. And this likewiſe doth argue want of bowels in thoſe, who, for an opinion that is not fundamentall, will endanger the publick good. Certainly, when the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Haſt thou faith? Have it to thy ſelf,</hi> he ſuppoſeth it becomes the modeſty of a man to keep that opinion to himſelfe, which differeth from all others. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> reproving the Chriſtians that would needleſly profeſſe their faith, though it endangered their lives, hath a good ſaying, <hi>Confiteri nos magis voluit Chriſtus, quàm profiteri;</hi> Chriſt would have us confeſſe, rather then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe: he confeſſeth, that doth it being called, and put upon it; he profeſſeth, that doth it of his own accord. <hi>Homer</hi> feigned wittily, that <hi>Jupiter</hi> took <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (the goddeſſe of ſtrife) by the hair, and threw her out of heaven, whereby they had peace: O! throw this <hi>Alecto</hi> out of Church and State.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>To paſſe by much ingratitude and unthankefulneſſe of people.</hi> Thus the mother doth at the childes hand: and ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> doth with the Iſraelites at other times.
<q>
                  <hi>Si quoties peccant homines</hi> —</q> ſaid hee of God. Labour to be content with the reward of a good conſcience, and glory with God, how unkind and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſoever people be. That cuſtome of <hi>Ostraciſmus,</hi> baniſhing men of great deſerts and abilities, was onely becauſe of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious ſore eyes of the people, that could not bear ſuch worth: Fatherly affections will not give over for this. Wee read in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of the Heathens, that, for ſuch diſcourteſies, would take ſnuffe, and endeavour to ruine the publick; but this will be farre from a godly, fatherly diſpoſition. And, certainly, if we can read of Chriſt enduring the contradiction of ſinners, and dying for them who did revile him and reproach him; how well may Magiſtrates bear with the peoples ingratitude?</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113455:8"/> 9. <hi>To execute juſtice upon offenders and enemies.</hi> Hee that loveth the ſheep, will kill the wolves, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.35. Yea, to abound in all kind of juſtice, diſtributive, and commutative. This is more glorious then the morning-ſtarre; which makes the Scripture call ſo diligently upon all in place to execute it: This makes the oppreſſed and injured to love you. What was the cauſe that the Egyptians made the bird <hi>Ibis</hi> their God, but becauſe, by her horned bill, ſhee killed thoſe venemous creatures that had annoyed them? The Eagle, though an excellent creature, yet was counted unclean, becauſe of his rapine and violence upon others. How lovely is that carriage of <hi>Jobs,</hi> deſcribed in ſeverall verſes, <hi>Job</hi> 29. from <hi>ver.</hi> 7. to the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>?</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>To venture againſt all fears and dangers.</hi> Thus the father and mother doe for their little ones, chuſing it ſhould rather fall upon themſelves, then the fruit of their loins: Thus wee ſee <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> not daunted at any oppoſitions; their zeal for the publick made them, like <hi>Job</hi>'s Leviathan, laugh at the ſpear. To go againſt friends, relations, enemies, for to ſave the publick, argueth a fatherly couragious heart; <hi>Praeſis ut proſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>To haſten the accompliſhment of their miſery. Luther</hi> called peace, <hi>Coelum, &amp; Paradiſum,</hi> a very Heaven, and Paradiſe; but it muſt be a peace which doth not divorce it ſelfe from truth: <hi>Maledicta ſit illa pax</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hierome):</hi> nor <hi>in qua involutum est bellum.</hi> They are therefore ſo to haſten it, as God ſpeaks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the accompliſhment of mercies for his people, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.22. <hi>I the Lord will haſten it in his time. Hezekiah</hi> hath an emphaticall expreſſion about the Kingdomes calamity in his time, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37.3. where the land is compared to a woman in travell, that is tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with many pangs and throbs: now we know what care and induſtry uſeth to be taken in ſuch extremities. The heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodies communicate their influence not in <hi>quantum cailda, ſed in quantum velocis motûs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grounds.</hi> 1. <hi>From the example of God and Chriſt himſelf.</hi> No wonder <hi>Moſes</hi> is to be ſo tender, when God himſelf is ſo, <hi>Deu.</hi> 32.10, 11, 12. where God is ſaid to <hi>finde</hi> his people as ſo many ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſheep; to <hi>lead him about,</hi> or to <hi>compaſſe</hi> him, as the Greek tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateth it. Thus <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 32.7. <hi>Thou wilt compaſſe me about
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113455:9"/>with ſafe deliverance: Hee kept them as the apple of his eye;</hi> that is, with all diligent care. And this providence of God is further reſembled to the Eagle, which <hi>fluttereth over her young ones:</hi> It is the ſame word with <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. <hi>[The Spirit of God moved;]</hi> ſo that it implyeth the cheerfull influence which God put into them: <hi>Shee taketh them</hi> (if they be negligent) <hi>and beareth them upon her wings,</hi> not in her talons, wherewith ſhe carrieth her prey. See in this paſſage a lively deſcription, what Governours in place and office ſhould be to their people. Thus <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.3, 4. <hi>I taught E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim to goe, taking them by their arms: — and I was unto them as they that take off the yoke on their jaws, and I laid meat to them.</hi> Here Gods government is deſcribed to be full of meekneſſe: he uſed them not as beaſts, but children; yea, he took off the yokes others had put on. And as for Chriſts government over his people, how gentle that is, appeareth <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.10. <hi>Hee ſhall gather his lambs in his arm, and carry them in his boſome, and ſhall gently lead thoſe that are with young:</hi> Hee therefore ſaid truely, <hi>Nulla creatura humilior Chriſto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>From the greatneſſe of that God to whom all in place and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice are accountable.</hi> Howſoever, when men in place look beneath them, they may be apt to puffe up themſelves, and grow lofty; yet, comparatively, to God they are nothing. <hi>All the Nations of the world are but a drop;</hi> and how little art thou, who art not the thouſand part of that drop? The Scripture delighteth to ſpeak of Gods greatneſſe to men; for till God be great to us, every man and power is great: but nothing is great to him, to whom God is great. <hi>According to thy fear, ſo is thy wrath:</hi> by <hi>fear</hi> may be meant the word of God, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. <hi>The fear of the Lord is excellent:</hi> ſo that Gods wrath is ſo great as the word revealeth it, though men may deſpiſe or leſſen it. Conſider dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently that place <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.21, 22, 23. We ſhall not govern with contemptuous carriage, when we apprehend that we are but as ſo much ſmall duſt, which God will blow away when he pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. It is with men, as with letters that have great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſuperſcriptions, <hi>(Right Honourable,</hi> &amp;c.) but, when open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there is nothing but a little black ink, and duſt upon them: ſo, though men have great places and offices; yet within there is but a little black bloud, and duſt to cover it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:113455:9"/> 3. <hi>This is the onely way to have the hearts and conſciences of people.</hi> Piety and juſtice doe onely convince men, when all carnall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies will be like a blazing ſtarre, that makes a great gaze for a while, but endeth at laſt in ſlime and noiſomeneſſe. <hi>Herod</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>John,</hi> becauſe he was a juſt and holy man. When the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and affections of a people are to their Governours, they are tyed by ſtronger bonds then power or fear can put upon them. How ſucceſſefull then will it prove, when, as God (by raiſing up of men to places) gives them the titles of God; ſo likewiſe he communicateth unto them the juſtice, the holineſſe of a God, by which the people are kept in awe and love? Some Heathens, before they went to warre, ſacrificed to <hi>Love;</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, that none would truly fight, but thoſe that had love to the Common-wealth: and ſo it holdeth in all other pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick actions. Let men therefore in place and office ſo deport themſelves, that all the people may cry out, and ſay, God ſo love you and yours, as you have loved us, and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>This is a ſure clear way to keep from confuſion. They that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve lying vanities, forſake their own mercy,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jonah</hi> by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. A plain upright way proveth in the event, to all the owners thereof, the beſt policy. Commentators obſerve of <hi>David,</hi> that he was never brought into ſtreights, but when he left Gods way: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>Then I ſhall not be confounded, when I have reſpect to all the commandements.</hi> A man ſhall never be brought to this, <hi>O wretch that I am!</hi> Would to God I had taken another way, or another ſide. It is a ſad thing to read of <hi>Tully,</hi> when he ſaw all publick events to make againſt him, complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>O turpem ſenectutem! O me nunquam ſapientem!</hi> And to ſuch a tragicall end have many meer Polititians been brought: <hi>Lege historiam, nè fias hiſtoria,</hi> ſaid hee. It was <hi>Gregory Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzene</hi>'s meditation by the ſea-ſide, when he ſaw many fiſhes car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with the ſtream; they were hurried upon the land, then a torrent would fetch them off again, preſently they would be landed again; but he obſerved other fiſhes that ſtuck to a rock, and they were alwaies in the ſame place, howſoever the waves did rage and rowle up and down: Thus hee applied it; The former ſort of fiſhes were like men that adhere to theſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113455:10"/>fading creatures, and the latter to thoſe that ſtick faſt to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fabius Maximus,</hi> though a Soothſayer, yet would ſay, <hi>Opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis auſpiciis ea geri, quae pro ſalute Reipublicae gerentur; quae contra Rempub. ferrentur, contra auſpicia ferri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What did <hi>Ahithophel</hi> get by his carnall wiſdome? Might he not ſay as <hi>Jonathan, Behold, I have tasted a little honey, and now I muſt die?</hi> I have injoyed a little applauſe and greatneſſe, and now I muſt be damned?</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>The greater places of truſt, the greater are our accounts. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut creſcunt dona, ſic creſcunt rationes donorum:</hi> Where God giveth more, there he requireth more. O, let every one then that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ſteare the ſhip, eſpecially in theſe tempeſts and ſtorms, imitate <hi>Solomon,</hi> praying unto God for wiſdome to adminiſter that office: and this was ſo acceptable to God, that hee gave him all other abundance. Take heed leſt the Divell ſet thee not up upon the pinnacle of the Temple, hoping to throw thee down headlong. You are, at the day of judgement, not onely to give an account for your perſonall ſins, but Common-wealth ſins: O, tremble in the thoughts of ſuch an account. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaid well, <hi>Deſcendamus in infernum viventes, nè deſcendamus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientes:</hi> Let us goe into hell while we are alive, by meditation and conſideration, leſt we go into it while we are dead. How neceſſary is it that you, whoſe labour and praiſe it is to ſet the Church and State at liberty, ſhould have your own hearts alſo at liberty from all corrupt aimes and reſpects? Be not offended at theſe things; <hi>Genus quoddam martyri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> est non ignobile, reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes aequanimiter ferre:</hi> It is a noble kind of martyrdome, to bear reproofs patiently.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Their Titles and Names are for this duty.</hi> Hence they are called <hi>gods,</hi> and <hi>fathers:</hi> their government is ſaid to be <hi>feeding;</hi> yea, the King of Tyre is called <hi>Cherub,</hi> either ironically, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he thought ſo, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.14. for, as God doth give ſometimes the names from earthly powers to Angels, as when they are called <hi>thrones,</hi> and <hi>dominions, Col.</hi> 1.16. ſo he doth take the names of thoſe heavenly ſpirits, and adorneth Governours in the earth with them. Now they are ſpirits of ſervice to others; that, as the Sun hath its name from a word that ſignifieth <hi>to adminiſter,</hi> and <hi>to be ſerviceable,</hi> becauſe the light is not for it ſelfe, but others;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113455:10"/>ſo likewiſe all the power and honour that God giveth men is for the publick, and not for themſelves: Let therefore new ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and places raiſe up the heart to ſutable operations; and upon miſcarriages, let us reflect, and ſay, How ill doth this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and title agree together?</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Acts of unrighteouſneſſe have a great guilt:</hi> for they are not onely againſt a ſpirituall conſcience, but a naturall; and when that is awakened, what adoe is there to have it graciouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed? When <hi>Paul</hi> preached of <hi>juſtice,</hi> and <hi>temperance,</hi> ſinnes which a naturall conſcience doth condemne, he made <hi>Felix</hi> to tremble. Though you have a priviledge (Honourable, and Worthy) that no man can arreſt or implead you; yet you know full well, that there is no priviledge from the arreſts of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the impleading of Gods word. It is neceſſary to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, we have to doe with God and not man: and if <hi>Socrates,</hi> though an Heathen, could riſe up to that reſolution, <hi>I will obey God rather then men</hi> (the very ſame words which the Apoſtle u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed); how much rather ought Chriſtians?</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>The people doe expect this from them,</hi> even as they doe that the Sun ſhould ſhine, and the clouds rain. For this they give themſelves and their families to be plundred and undone, that piety and righteouſneſſe may be eſtabliſhed. When they come up hither out of the Countrey, they think they are come to the gates of the kingdome of heaven, where righteouſneſſe ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently enter: they forget all the pangs and troubles their ſoules have travelled in, becauſe of the hopes of that man-childe of Reformation which ſhall be brought forth. They think, when they have been ſtung by any ſerpents full of poiſon and venome, it is but their looking upon you, and they ſhould be healed preſently. <hi>Solomons</hi> adminiſtration is excellently deſcribed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.6. <hi>Hee ſhall come down like rain upon the mowen graſſe:</hi> The Originall word ſignifieth alſo <hi>a ſhorn fleece of wooll;</hi> and ſome make it an alluſion to <hi>Gideons</hi> fleece, that had dew fell on it: but it may well be retained as in our Tranſlation; for the graſſe mowen craveth rain, as the people did righteouſneſſe; and the Pſalmiſt doth again expreſſe this righteouſneſſe by <hi>ſhowres.</hi> The word is uſed only in this place, and hath its ſignification of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſing, hereby repreſenting the ſcattering of juſtice abroad, as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113455:11"/>the drops of raine are to make fertill the ground.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> Suffer (worthy Patriots) a word of exhortation from what hath been ſaid: Certainly, if ever, here are occaſions and objects of all the graces requiſite in ſuch offices. So walk and doe, that the Common-wealth may look upon you as their <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs,</hi> their <hi>Moſeſſes,</hi> their <hi>Mordecaies.</hi> Humble your ſelves this day before God for any neglect or omiſſion. What hath been done with publick affections, and unbyaſſed reſpects to God and his cauſe, will be incredible joy and gladneſſe to you afterwards. Obſerve how much <hi>Nehemiah</hi> refreſhed himſelfe with this, <hi>Neh.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Think upon mee, my God, for good, according to all that I have done for this people.</hi> So Chap. 13.14. <hi>Remember mee, O my God, and wipe not out the good deeds that I have done for the houſe of my God.</hi> So ver. 22. <hi>Remember me according to this, and ſpare me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the greatneſſe of thy mercy:</hi> and ver. 31. <hi>Remember mee, O my God, for good.</hi> See here what comfortable incouragements he hath: Is not this more then if the King had given him ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Provinces and Kingdomes to rule over? Thus <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 20.3. when he heard the ſentence of death paſſed upon him, what ſupported him, but an upright heart in that Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation he had begun? I know the heart ſet upon great things in the world, is apt to contemn theſe truths of God, as too pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillanimous, and emaſculating their courage: But, as <hi>Dionyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> (if I miſtake him not) who, being a Stoick, wrote a book, that <hi>pain</hi> was nothing, it was but an imagination; yet when he fell ſick of the Stone, and felt the torture of it, he cryed out, All that he had written was falſe, as he now felt by experience: So men, who, in their life times, have greedily purſued the great and glorious things of this world; when dying, when appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before God, will cry out, They were but all dreams, and imaginations: And this deſtroyeth men, that they take theſe things as the words of meer men, and beleeve them not as the undeniable truths of God: even as young <hi>Samuel</hi> thought the voice he heard to be the voice of <hi>Eli,</hi> of a man, and no more; therefore goeth to ſleep again, till he underſtood it to be the voice of God. Conſider likewiſe the honour that God puts upon you, when he makes you inſtruments to relieve the oppreſſed Church and State. If a drop of cold water ſhall not go without
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113455:11"/>a reward, how acceptable then will it be, when men have been ready to give many drops of their warm bloud? God, when he made heaven and earth, took no inſtruments, no not Angels themſelves, in that work of Creation; but when he makes <hi>new heavens,</hi> and <hi>new earth,</hi> (as the Scripture phraſe is about the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and good change of a Kingdome) he putteth much glory upon thoſe who are ſubſervient therein.</p>
            <p>Again, meditate on the difficulty and rarity of this diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and affection in men of truſt. How few are there that look upon themſelves as for the publick, and not the publick for themſelves? Yea, and ſuppoſe we be mounted up ſo high by generous principles, as to give the preheminence to the publick; yet to do this with godly, ſincere aims and ends, is a further dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty. <hi>Jehu,</hi> how high did he go in a Reformation? yet would not yeeld to take away <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s Calves, though hee did zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly deſtroy <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts.</p>
            <p>Thus it is an eaſier matter to conſent that the Antichriſtian yoke and burden ſhall be removed, then to ſet up Chriſts order and government. But when our Saviour invited thoſe that were heavie laden and burdened (under the Phariſaicall government and traditions) as ſome learned men expound it; leſt they ſhould think this were all, he bids them take his yoke upon them. Mens corruptions may make them willing to have An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt pulled down; yea, their advantages and ſelf-intereſts may incline them that way: but there are required many poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive graces to ſet up the wayes and orders of Chriſt. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, there was ſomething in it, that the Heathens did ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally object againſt the Chriſtian Religion and way, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with Common-wealths and Magiſtracy; not that indeed there was any contradiction: but onely it is hard for States to bring up every thing in their Kingdome to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture way. This muſt be laid down as a moſt certain principle, (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) that <hi>Gods word will not attemper it ſelf, or condeſcend to Princes and States, but they must bring themſelves to that.</hi> And therefore we ought the more earneſtly to ſtrive in prayer unto God for ſuch that are in authority, and to rejoyce in ſeeing the cluſters of grapes, though as yet wee are not entered into Canaan. Now let mee inſtance in ſome particulars, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113455:12"/>your tender bowels may be wonderfully expreſſed: As,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>In the ſetting up of a faithfull, learned Miniſtry in all the parts of the Kingdome:</hi> And, bleſſed be God, you have ſhewed much readineſſe to this work. It was your enemies deſigne to put that down, although it proved a work as impoſſible to them, as to put fetters and gyves upon the Sun, to hinder it in its courſe. Herein our Saviour ſhewed his bowels, and imitate him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.36, 37. The people then injoyed the reading of the Scriptures every Sabbath day, with the Phariſees explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it: that was not wholly unuſefull (for then our Saviour would not have bid the people heare them); yet, for all this, his bowels yearned to them, as ſheep without a ſhepherd. What pity is it, to have a great harveſt, and no labourers to inne it? The Miniſters are the <hi>light</hi> and <hi>ſalt</hi> of the earth; and how neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary are they, eſpecially if wee conſider the great darkneſſe, and unſavoury manners of moſt people? Theſe are like <hi>Orpheus,</hi> to uſe the harp of Gods word, whereby thoſe who are as wilde as beaſts, and ſtupid as trees, may be new-moulded, and become the people of God. Some have thought, that therefore Chriſt would uſe ſpittle in the curing of the blind man, to ſhew, that it muſt be ſomething which goeth out of his mouth, the word preached, that would indeed give the true eye-ſight: But I will not abide by that notion.</p>
            <p>A ſecond thing wherein compaſſionate bowels may be ſeen, is, as much as lyeth in you, to <hi>ſtop the infection and contagion of hereſies.</hi> How many men are there, who may be called, as <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> was, <hi>Centauri,</hi> for the divers monſtrous opinions they hold? There is a Book, called, <hi>The compaſſionate Samaritan,</hi> who makes it a great act of pity, to give an unbounded and illimited tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to every man: But, certainly, this is ſuch a pity as St. <hi>Francis</hi> had, that would take the beggars lice, and put them into his own boſome. The Scripture ſpeaketh much of the cordiall affections that ought to be in us againſt them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. <hi>Though we, or an Angel ſhould preach any other doctrine, let him be accurſed.</hi> So again, 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 10, 11. <hi>If there come any unto you, and bring not this doctrine, receive him not into your houſe, nor bid him God ſpeed:</hi> and mark the reaſon, <hi>He that biddeth him God ſpeed, is partaker of his evill deeds:</hi> Hee calleth evill doctrines <hi>evill deeds</hi> there.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113455:12"/>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Thou canſt not bear them which are evill, and thou hast tryed them which ſay, they are Apoſtles, and are not:</hi> ſo <hi>ver.</hi> 14, 15. Its made their ſin, that they had ſuch as taught the doctrine of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> and others. Learn of this <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 9.9. How did he mourn before the Lord, faſting forty dayes and nights, becauſe the people had committed idolatry in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence? Not but that inſtruction by way of reaſon, ought to goe before all rejection of them. It is the Apoſtles rule, To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke in all doctrine; ſo that there are none who would have the ſuppreſſion of hereſies and errours, but they likewiſe preſſe a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall admonition and information, that ſo the obſtinacy of men gainſaying may appear to all the world. <hi>Muſculus</hi> hath a memorable ſtory in his Common-place <hi>de haereſi,</hi> that there were ſome Anabaptiſts, who had been four yeers in priſon, and there were ſome who cried to have them put to death; but others, more moderate, dealt with them by way of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and in ſuch a ſpirit of meekneſſe, that they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced their ſalvation, and not confuſion was ſought for: And by this means they changed their mindes, and one, being a pretty ſcholar, was choſen Deacon in a Church, and by his means ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more were drawn from Anabaptiſme. It's no diſparagement to the Reformation, but rather an argument of the truth of it, that when the good ſeed is ſown, the Divell is ſo induſtrious to ſow his tares. The April ſhowres, that make the graſſe grow, and the flowers ſweet, do likewiſe cauſe many croaking frogs to come forth: But as this is not to be caſt upon the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo ought thoſe that are in authority to be the more vigilant, knowing, that then Satan is more buſie then ever: The tares were ſown when men were aſleep.</p>
            <p>Again, Look to this, That while you ſuppreſſe hereſies, you ſtill leave a way for the improvement and growth of mens a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities and parts, leſt in time it be thought hereſie, to have more learning then another; as, when Reformation began, the Papiſts made it a ſuſpicion of hereſie, to underſtand Greek and Hebrew.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Let not every opinion in matters of leſſe conſequence, be accounted hereſie: for then it will fall out, as among one kind of people, that made only Treaſon capitall, and to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113455:13"/>by death; but then the Judges had a device to finde every offence Treaſon, and ſo indeed all ſins were capitall. Theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſuch like, laid down, you ought to be zealous and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous againſt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another <hi>Uſe</hi> may be to us Miniſters: For, certainly, we need as much the preſſing of publick affections upon us as any other. How hardly doe we finde ſuch bowels in us, as were in <hi>Paul? Gal.</hi> 4.19. <hi>My little children, of whom I travell in birth again.</hi> So 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>We were gentle among you, even as the nurſe cheriſheth her children:</hi> thus <hi>Paul,</hi> whom <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> calls <hi>the terrestriall Angel;</hi> yea, more, <hi>Cor Pauli eſt cor Chriſti.</hi> And, certainly, if theſe bowels were in us, it would keep us from pride, ſelf-ſeeking, and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: And what is preached from inward bowels doth more good, then things of meer invention and parts, how excellent ſoever; as the milk that cometh warm out of the breſt nouriſheth more then that which is heated at the fire. What a ridiculous thing was that of <hi>Bernard,</hi> to excommunicate flies, becauſe they were troubleſome to a Chappell? And how cruelly hath that ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſword been drawn out in Popery, meerly for want of bowels? So that in preaching, diſpenſation of Sacraments, and infliction of ſpirituall cenſures, there is required much prudence, zeal, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, love, all which cannot be done without tender bowels and compaſſions. Many times wee Miniſters are like <hi>Samſons</hi> dead Lion, though others may finde honey in us, yet we our ſelves feel not the ſweetneſſe of it. Chriſt ſaid thrice to <hi>Peter, Feed my ſheep;</hi> but not once, <hi>Milk them,</hi> or, <hi>Shear them.</hi> So that I know not what more neceſſary to be prayed for this day, then to ſay, Give, Lord, to Magiſtrates, give to Miniſters, give to Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, give to Souldiers: What ſhalt thou give them? Fatherly bowels. This will be a living ſpring to carry us forward in our work, when all other principles are but a land-floud, that will quickly be dried up. Many diſputes, diviſions, and jealouſies would be extinct, if this inward love were effectuall. The bowels of the true mother will by no means endure the ſword ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the childe. I ſhall conclude, deſiring to all that temper which <hi>Paul</hi> commends in <hi>Timothy, Phil.</hi> 2.20. naturally to take care for the publick; and ſo ſhall we avoid that charge the Apoſtle layeth upon many, that they <hi>ſeek their own, and not the things of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113455:13"/>
            <p> I come to the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Obſervation, which is, that <hi>The ingratitude and diſcontent of people is ſuch under Reformers, that they make their Governours lives hard and miſerable. Moſes,</hi> though a man noted for ſuch meekneſſe, yet is quite wearied out with the work; and ſometimes the people talk of ſtoning him, as the cauſe of all their calamity. They could not be more bitter and violent againſt <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his task-maſters, then now they are againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> Thus they deal with their Worthies, as beaſts with trees, that run to ſhelter themſelves under them while the ſtorm and tempeſt is, and after that is over, then they browze upon the boughs, and break down the branches thereof. So that there is no ſafe rule to go by in publick adminiſtrations: not ſelf-inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſts, not preſent ſucceſſe, not applauſe of the people; but a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eying and owning of God in all.</p>
            <p>In the amplifying of this Doctrine, wee will take notice of the particulars, Wherein, and How the Iſraelites murmured under the faithfull conduct of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Their murmuring is excellently deſcribed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.2. to be a beaſtly ſin; for the word doth ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifie ſuch howlings as beaſts uſe to make when they are ready to be famiſhed. What an horrid noiſe do dogs and ſuch crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures make? the ſame did the Iſraelites againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, Conſider, they charge their Governours as the cauſe of the calamities that are come upon them. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.13. <hi>Moſes</hi> is there charged with a deſigne to bring them out of Egypt to kill them in the wilderneſſe, and that he intended to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Prince over them: and mark their expreſſion, <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>Wilt thou put out the eyes of theſe men?</hi> that is, Doe you think ſo to blind them, that they ſhould not eſpie out your fraud? O hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ingratitude! <hi>Moſes</hi> was much incenſed at this: and ſee how his integrity comforted him, <hi>I have not taken one aſſe from them</hi> (the vileſt beaſt) <hi>nor hurt one of them.</hi> Thus the good Prophets were judged the <hi>troublers of Iſrael:</hi> Thus the ignorant people blame the Phyſick and Phyſician, as if they made them ſick, when it is the corrupt humour within. And are there not men now adaies, that, in ſtead of charging their Idolatries, Oaths, and Blaſphemies, as the cauſes of the miſerable calamities upon us, lay all the blame upon thoſe that would reform things amiſſe?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113455:14"/> 2. Though the ſervants of God laboured by arguments to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay their frowardneſſe, yet this melodious harp could not drive out that evill ſpirit in them, <hi>Num.</hi> 14.9, 10. <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.9. Though they were told what great things God had done for them: though they make it appear, God had forſaken their enemies; yet they hearken to nothing. To bid men in diſtreſſe not conſider the dead womb of the creature, but the power of God, is as ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to their carnall hearts, as that mock-charity <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of, which ſaith, <hi>Goe home and be warmed,</hi> but doth nothing at all. Though you draw buckets of water out of the wels of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, yet you can hardly quench the fire of impatiency, when it hath inflamed a people.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third expreſſion of their diſcontent, is, To magnifie their former life, though never ſo miſerable. <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.3. <hi>When we ſate down by the fleſh-pots: Sate down;</hi> as if they had ſuch eaſe and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: not one word of their brick and ſtraw. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.13. They tell <hi>Moſes,</hi> he had brought them <hi>out of a land that flowed with milk and honey.</hi> That which was an iron furnace, in which they groaned, and were weary of their lives, they here call, <hi>A land flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with milk and honey;</hi> the ſame phraſe that is given to Canaan: And are there not many ſuch mutiners to this day amongſt us? Have not people forgotten the preſſures, the State and Church burdens, that once they crouched under? Did they not long for a redemption? and now when it is working for them, they make an Egypt as good as a Canaan.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To be willing, for their eaſe-ſake, to go back to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition again. <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Let us make our ſelves a Captain, and go down into Egypt.</hi> And doth not many a man wiſh for the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh innovations again, rather then to be undone thus continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, as they account it? But, what good would peace and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty doe to a gracious heart, if he muſt drink again of ſtreams muddied by the inventions of men, and have gravell again put into the bread he muſt eat? Certainly, corrupt Doctrine and Worſhip is more to be feared then the devouring ſword.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They are onely diſcontented, becauſe of outward ſtreights and miſeries; and when indeed they ſhould complain, we have not a word fall from them. When <hi>Aaron</hi> was indeed in blame, for making a golden calfe, they could bear that well enough:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113455:14"/>When he ſaid, <hi>To morrow ſhall be a feast to the Lord,</hi> none opened his mouth, crying, It is Idolatry, we dare not do it: but, in hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and drought, in want of neceſſaries, then they fret and rage. Thus, people that open their mouthes becauſe of taxes and aſſeſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, found no trouble or burden under thoſe altars, cringes, and corrupt doctrines that were then preached. When our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates are gone, we think our ſelves undone; but not ſo, when God and his pure worſhip is removed from us.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In all their murmurings, they never blame themſelves for their ſins: ſometimes they complain of God, of the inſtruments, of the evils themſelves; but never any word of their own ſins. If they had ſaid, God hath done like an holy and juſt God, our Governours like faithfull and wiſe men; but we, by our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, have brought all this evill upon our ſelves, it had been well. It argueth a carnall froward heart, when we are alwayes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining, and talking againſt inſtruments, never ſeriouſly hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling our ſelves for our ſins, nor conſidering, that if God doe leave Governours to their own ſelves, it is for the ſins of the people. What makes our hearts like ſo many Mount Aetnaes, ſending forth vollies of enraged flames; but looking upon mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies as ſo many debts to us, and calamities as ſo many injuries? Let us feel ſin more, and we ſhall feel outward troubles leſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. Of admonition to people, to <hi>take heed of this ſin of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring and diſcontent.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>Neither murmure ye</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>as ſome of them murmured.</hi> It is queſtioned, how this was applicable to the Corinthians; Why ſhould they <hi>murmure?</hi> And it is anſwered thus; The Corinthians were guilty of many foule and diſorderly courſes: now the falſe Apoſtles let them alone; but <hi>Paul</hi> he was reſolved to come with the rod of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline among them (as he ſaith): hereupon the Corinthians mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, their ſore eyes could not endure the Sun ſhining: And this is ſtill the cauſe of the vexations and diſquietneſſe of men, that they cannot ſubmit to the holy rules and wayes of Chriſt. This made ſome heretofore call the <hi>Geneva Diſcipline</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition;</hi> and all becauſe men love their luſts and their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures even to death. Grudge not therefore under the difficulty of a Reformation. Think not, that God will caſt England into a dead ſleep, as he did once <hi>Adam,</hi> and take out of her ſide a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113455:15"/>glorious Church, and ſhee never know of it, or feel any pain. Conſider how much the Antichriſtian party ventureth for their Idols and corrupt worſhip; how they, through many tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, enter into the kingdome of hell, and the kingdome of darkneſſe ſuffereth violence by them: they deny themſelves, and take up the croſſe, and follow Satan. O that we were as wiſe, as cordiall, had as publick affections for the truths and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Chriſt, as they for Satan. Shall men bring their ear-rings to make a golden calf; yea, offer their ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to <hi>Molech?</hi> And ſhall not we be ready to do and ſuffer in the way God calleth for?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. Of direction to men in place and truſt, To <hi>expect diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and hardſhip.</hi> You ſee <hi>Moſes</hi> is even weary of his life. <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuah</hi> indeed, never met with any diſcontent or muttering from the people (herein God was very mercifull unto him.) But <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> what difficulties did they devour? Be you as the heavens, that communicate their influence to the earth; though that, by way of requitall, ſends up nothing but black and ſmoaky vapours. Now in the midſt of theſe, take ſome Remedies:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider ſeriouſly, <hi>Whether you have not ſinned against God, and therefore God makes the people looſe in their affections.</hi> When <hi>Shimei</hi> reviled <hi>David,</hi> ſee how ſpiritually <hi>David</hi> reſenteth it: <hi>The Lord bid him do it.</hi> There is not any ſigh or diſcontent in people, but there is a juſt and wiſe providence in it, though it may be their fault and impatiency. It is a great expreſſion of Gods love to the people of Iſrael, that <hi>a dog</hi> ſhould <hi>not move his tongue againſt man or beast,</hi> Exod. 11.7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Keep up ſincerity, and holy ends in reference to God.</hi> How could <hi>Moſes</hi> have ſupported himſelf, if there had not been that brazen wall therein? O how ſweet a repoſe is it to a man much in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick affairs, when hee can truly empty his ſoul in prayer to God! O Lord, the people are jealous and ſuſpicious, many have hard thoughts, but thou knoweſt the integrity of my heart and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours: O Lord, I have not ſought my ſelf, nor been vainly puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed up. I have made no parties, driven on no deſignes; but cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially thought, meditated, and indeavoured the publick good; <hi>Remember me, O my God, in this.</hi> Such a man God will honour,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113455:15"/>and he hath the advantage of all others who ſerve corrupt ends. And, truly, ſuch is the change of all ſublunary things, while they are at the beſt, that there is no ſafe haven but in this one thing.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Conſider this or <hi>Moſes; As ſoon as the people were out of Egypt, and they became to be an embodied people, the firſt thing he ſets upon by the command of God, is to ſettle the Worſhip of God, and order therein:</hi> for the Church of God, being a Society joining together to worſhip God, it cannot be rationally thought, that it ſhould remain compact together without Government, no more then any other Society. And it is one thing, when God raiſeth up ſome to be avenged on the ſins and oppreſſions of men that have gone before; and another thing, when, beſides this, God putteth into their heart to ſettle the things of his Temple: The firſt is a mercy, and this was done by <hi>Jehu:</hi> the ſecond is a far greater mercy, and that was done by <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Joſiah.</hi> Now our conſidence and expectation is, that God will uſe you as inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for both theſe mercies to the Kingdome: And, oh that in this Land, at laſt, we might (as <hi>Paul</hi> concerning the Coloſſians, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.) rejoice, beholding the faith and order thereof.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
